בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, so we start סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* דף כ"ו *Daf
Kaf Vav*, we start three lines from the bottom of כ"ה עמוד
ב' *Kaf He Amud Bet*. אבוה דרבי זירא עבד גביותא תריסר שנין
*Avud d’Rabbi Zeira avid givyusa treisar shanin*. So we were talking about
tax collectors. So it says the father of רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira*,
he was a tax collector for 13 years for the government. כי
הוי אתי ריש נהרא למתא *Ki havei asi reish nahara l’massa*, and
we said a סתם stam *stam* tax collector is כשר kasher *kosher*
until we see that he takes too much money, you know, that
he puts too much in his pocket. So כי הוי ריש נהרא
למתא *ki havei reish nahara l’massa* when the head of the locale,
you know, literally of the river or whatever, you know, came to
the city, כי הוי חזי רבנן *ki havei chazi rabbanan*, so then
when the father of רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira* saw the rabbis, so
he knew this guy was going to try to now so to
say, hey, you know, you need to be collecting more taxes. Apparently
he was protecting the people of the city and saying, you know,
and giving very little, demanding very little taxes and giving very little
taxes to the government, okay? So what would he do now the
guy was coming to
pay a surprise visit? So when he saw the rabbis, אמר ליה
amar lei, *amar lei*: ליכו מבאבא דחדירייכו *Leichu m’bava d’chedreichu*. You know,
go hide, go hide into your rooms like they shouldn't see rabbis
out there, and then he'll say, hey, what are all these rabbis?
They're not paying their taxes. Maybe he gave rabbis an exemption or
whatever. Go hide, don't let anybody, don't let him see you. כי
הוי חזי אינש דמתא *Ki havei chazi inish d’massa* and when he
the father of רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira* saw the normal townspeople, אמר
Amar *amar*: ריש נהרא למתא *Reish nahara l’massa* hey, the boss is
coming, the boss is coming, so not the boss is coming everybody
get to work, the boss is coming, והאידנא נחיס אבא לפום ברא
*v’idnan nachis aba l’fumban* and what's going to happen is a father
will be slaughtered in the presence of his son, ברא לפום אבא
*bra l’fum aba* and a son in the presence of his father,
meaning he's going to put these very heavy taxes on you, he's
going to be upset that we haven't collected enough taxes,
so you know, your all lives are at stake. ומיגלז כולי עלמא
*U-miglaz kulei alma*. So maybe he had to be a little bit
more explicit by the townspeople, by the rabbis he could give a
hint, right? See here also by the way, but notice also here
it's like it's not explicit, like there's some cryptic thing like, you
know, and therefore, so, you know, probably he didn't want, abandoned city?
What? Well, he wanted, you'll see what's going to happen, but what
I'm also saying is that he didn't want to be too explicit
because he didn't want to get in trouble. Like oh, I heard
you told all the townspeople to hide. Maybe he had other ways
of explaining what this was that he was saying. Okay, anyway, but
the result was everybody hid. Top of כ"ו עמוד א' *kaf vav
amud alef*. כי אתי *Ki asi*, so now the head of the
locale came, אמר ליה amar lei, *amar lei*, so he said, so
then he said: ממאן איבאי *Mimman ibei*? What do you mean that
I'm, you're complaining that I haven't given enough taxes? Who should I
ask the taxes from? This town has been abandoned, there's nobody around.
So don't blame me for not collecting enough taxes. כי נח נפשיה
*Ki naich nafshai* when he was passing away, אמר ליה *amar lei*:
שקולו תריסר מעי דצירי לי בסדינאי *Shkulu treisar ma’ei d’tsirei li b’sadinai*,
take these 13 מעה *ma'ah* that I've bound up in my, like,
in my kerchief, והדרו ליה לפלניא *v’hadru lei l’planya*, give it back
to so-and-so, דשקלינהו מיניה *d’shakalshinu minei* I took it from him for
tax payment, ולא אצטריך לי *v’lo istreik li* in the end of
the day I didn't need it, I was able
to get us off without having to pay it. So apparently holding
up what a truly righteous tax collector would look like.
Okay, moving on.
אמר פשט *Amar pshat*: בתחילה היו קוראים אותן אוצרי שביעית *Batchila hayu
korim otan otzrei shevi’is*. Originally they were called אוצרי שביעית *otzrei shevi'is*
and then they were called סוחרי שביעית sochrei shevi'is *sochrei shevi'is*. So
what does that mean? What's that shift from אוצרי שביעית *otzrei shevi'is*
to סוחרי שביעית *sochrei shevi'is*? מאי קאמר *Mai ka’amar*? אמר רב amar
Rav, יהודה הכי קאמר *Amar Rav Yehuda hachi ka’amar*: בתחילה היו אומרים
אוצרי שביעית כשרים ksherim סוחרים פסולים sochrim psulim *batchila hayu omrim otzrei
shevi’is ksheirim, sochrim psulim*. That if you're just gathering up your own
produce, you're כשר kasher *kosher*, even though maybe you'll leave it till
after the זמן הביעור *zman habiyur*, maybe you're not supposed to gather
it and protect it as if you're the owner, but you know,
that's not so bad. You're not doing business, you're just collecting your
own food, fruit. But if you're doing business, then you're פסול pasul,
*pasul*. משרבו הממציאים עמות לעניים ואזלי עניים aniyim ואספי להו *Mishe-rabu hamamtzi’ei
imos la’aniyim v’azli aniyim v’asfi lehu*, but then people basically what they
did was they paid the poor people, and the poor people went
out and they gathered up the שביעית *shevi'is* produce, and then they
brought it to this person. So he that was a type of
doing business. He wasn't doing the selling yet, but he was paying
people to collect it, but it didn't, you know, so that, but
they would say: oh, we're only gathering, we're not selling. So then
חזרו לומר אחד זה ואחד זה פסולים *chazru lomar echad zeh v’echad
zeh psulim*. Even if you're just gathering them up, you know, you're
פסול pasul. *pasul*. Obviously you're allowed to take for yourself, but somebody
who's clearly gathering it as an owner or gathering, you know, for
future business purposes and so on. קשו בה בני רחב *Kashu bah
b’nei Rechav*. So בני רחב *b'nei Rechav* didn't like this read of
the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. האי משרבו האנסים *Hai mishe-rabu ha’annasim*, it shouldn't
say when the forceful people became many, משרבו התגרי מיבעי ליה *mishe-rabu
ha-tagari mibayei lei*, it should be when the merchants became many, they
started expanding the category. אלא רבא *Ela rava*: בתחילה היו אומרים אחד
זה ואחד זה פסולים *batchila hayu omrim echad zeh v’echad zeh psulim*.
Originally they said whether you gather for yourself to keep it for
yourself, like you work, and or whether you're doing business, either way
it's פסול pasul *pasul*. But משרבו האנסים *mishe-rabu ha’annasim*, but once the
sort of, you know, the strong-arm people, ומהי ניהו ארנונא *u-mannu Arnona*,
when the need to pay taxes and the government started making demands,
after that happened כדמכריז רבי ינאי *k’dimachriz Rabbi Yannai*: פוקו וזרו בשביעית
*Puku v’ziru b’shevi’is*. Go and sow in שביעית *shevi'is*. go plant on
שמיטה shmita, משום ארנונא mishum arnona for the need of paying taxes
and that time now that people were working their field and gathering
you are allowed to or maybe you have to do that. So
you weren't going to say if a gatherer is פסול, pasul right
even if you harvest your own crops, you're supposed to leave it
for the עניים instead of leaving it you harvested. But you have
to do it because of this taxes. So in that time חזרו
לומר עוסקים כשרים chazru lomar oskim ksheirim fine. If you plant and
you gather which is the direct violation of שמיטה, shmita then you'll
still be כשר kasher because it's this period of paying the taxes.
Okay, but סוחרים פסולים still if you do business then you're פסול.
pasul. All right, now how are they doing this because of taxes?
So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafos, משרבו האנסין ומייני
ארנונא mishe-rabu ha-anassin u-may-nei arnona so this is what you get by
doing the בבלי Bavli you get it some more explicit in the
בבלי Bavli than the ירושלמי Yerushalmi but here's what תוספות Tosafos says.
ואם תאמר ve-im tomar but at least the ירושלמי Yerushalmi made it
clear that it sounded like their lives were at stake. That's not
in the בבלי Bavli right that's absent the idea that their lives
were at risk. So in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi you could say it
was a דאורייתא d'oraysa but they allowed it because their lives were
at risk. But in the בבלי Bavli you don't get a hint
that their lives were at risk. So let's look at what תוספות
Tosafos says. ואם תאמר משום ארנונא התירו לחרוש ולזרוע דהוי איסור דאורייתא
ve-im tomar mishum arnona hitiru lachrosh velizro'a dehavai issur d'oraysa they allowed
them to do a biblical violation? ויש לומר דמיירי בשביעית בזמן הזה
דרבנן ve-yesh lomar d'mairi b'shviis bizman hazeh derabbanan oh maybe nowadays it's
only rabbinic because the sanctity of the land depending on you know
different issues. אי נמי יש לומר דפיקוח נפש הוא ee nami yesh
lomar de-pikuach nefesh hu it was a their lives were at risk.
ששלח המלך מס ואין להם מה יפרענו ומתים בתפיסת המלך she-shalach hamelech
mas ve-ein lahem mah yifre'ennu u-metim bitfisas hamelech it doesn't say he'll
directly kill them, he'll throw them into prison and that could lead
to their death, right? הכי איתמר בירושלמי משום חיי נפש hachi itmar
bi-Yerushalmi mishum chayei nefesh now we learned the ירושלמי Yerushalmi did not
have the phrase חיי נפש. chayei nefesh. It's interesting תוספות Tosafos paraphrases
it like that but the ירושלמי Yerushalmi is clear that their lives
were at stake. So two very different interpretations: either their lives were
at stake or maybe it wasn't but they had to do it
but it was rabbinic and therefore because of this serious financial pressure
and so on it was allowed. This becomes an important גמרא Gemara
in the discussions of היתר מכירה. heter mechira. הרב קוק Rav Kook
uses you know relates to this גמרא Gemara a lot because if
you read the first reading of תוספות Tosafos that it was rabbinic
and it was allowed because of the economic pressure and so on
to pay the taxes right so then that can translate if we
assume nowadays as well that if we assume that it's the sanctity
is מדרבנן mi-d'rabbanan and שמיטה shmita is דרבנן d'rabbanan then given certain
pressures we can here they straight allowed violation you know so it's
even less if you're going to like try to do a trick
and sell the land and so on. In other words that's like
a workaround here they allowed direct violation. Okay so let's keep on
looking.
דאורייתא d'oraysa in a heavy heavy even like a crazy fine
so they had to do it. Presumably if there was if there
was no risk element right. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Now we're going to have some stories about this. רבי חייא בר
זרנוקי ורבי שמעון בן יהוצדק הוו קאזלו לעבר שנה באסיא. Rabbi Chiya
bar Zarnuki ve-Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak hava ka-azlu l'aber shana be-Asya. They
were going to do an עיבור שנה ibur shana to add a
month in אסיא. Asya. Now it was clear it was a שמיטה
shmita year. So תוספות Tosafos asks: wait a minute you're not supposed
to make a שמיטה shmita year extended right. If you remember you
don't want to extend a שמיטה shmita! year. So this is okay
maybe we'll see from the end of the story maybe they were
only going to sort of do the calculation not maybe for the
year after this not for this year itself. Anyway whatever. ופגעי u-pagi'u
the promise אסיא Asya is חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz you're not supposed
to do it in חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. Fine. So maybe it
was for the following year. פגע בהו ריש לקיש. paga behu Reish
Lakish. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish bumped into them. איטפל בהדייהו. itpil behadayhu.
He wanted to tag along. אמר איזיל איחזי היכי עבדי עובדא. amar
izil eichzei heichi avdi uvda. Let me go and see how they're
doing this. חזיא להו גברא דקא כרב. chazya lehu gavra de-ka karev.
Now as they were going presumably they were still in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael he saw a certain person who was plowing. אמר להו
כור כור בחורש. amar lehu kore kore be-choresh. This guy is plowing
and he's plowing the land on שמיטה! shmita Oh my god! אמרו
לו amru lo they said to him יכול לומר אגיסטון אני בתוכו.
yachol lomar agiston ani betocho. He could say from the word אגוסטוס
Augustus I am an imperial worker in the land. What does that
mean? So רש"י Rashi either says it means that I'm working for
a non-Jew which is interesting question: can a Jew work on שמיטה
shmita? in the land of a non-Jew?
Okay for a non-Jew right. Or let's take a look at תוספות.
Tosafos. אגיסטון אני בתוכו פירוש הקונטרס לשון ראשון שכיר אני
בתוכו בקרקע של נכרי הוא agiston ani betocho perush hakuntres lashon rishon
sachir ani betocho b'karka shel nochri hu ולא נהירא דמיהו בידינו מנכרי
בשביעית. ve-lo nahira de-mihu beyadeinu mi-nochri b'shviis. Okay
now how serious is that prohibition? Maybe it's not a biblical prohibition
whatever it is. Anyway one issue is can you work a non-Jew's
land in ישראל Yisrael on שמיטה? shmita? איכא נמי כפירוש
אחר שפירש משום ארנונא ika nami ke-perush acher she-peirash mishum arnona it's
back to the old explanation. I have to work I am like
I'm like a government worker because I have to work it in
order to pay the government tax. So effectively that's you know that's
why I'm doing it. I'm not doing it to make myself rich
I'm doing it because I'm forced to yes.
I can suggest that this might be someone who was forced to
work the land.
Right so אגיסטון agiston as of an imperial worker could mean directly
being forced. Meaning not just meaning literally like the government owns the
land. Not you're working סתם for a non-Jew and it's מותר. mutar.
The government owns the land and you're being you know compelled right
conscripted. Okay exactly. Right well again that gets to the question: is
it דאורייתא d'oraysa is it דרבנן d'rabbanan is your life at risk?
Okay. Okay so
anyway אגיסטון אני בתוכו. agiston ani betocho. תו חזיא להו גברא דהוה
קסח בתמרי. tu chazya lehu gavra de-hava ka-sach betamrei. He was pruning
in a vineyard. אמר ליה, a כהן וזומר? kohen v'zomeir? Oh my
God, a כהן kohen and he's pruning on שמיטה? shmita. אמר ליה,
they said to him, יכול לומר לעקבי סבא דאצר. yachol lomar l'akavei
saba d'atzar. No, I'm just pruning because I need the wood for
my olive press. I'm not doing it to actually tend to the
vines themselves. So אמר להם, amar lahem, he said to them, הלב
יודע אם לעקל אם לעקלקלות. halev yodeia im l'akel im l'akalkalot. The
heart knows whether you're doing it for your wood for your press
or whether you're doing it to deceive as a ruse. Okay. האי
אמר
לו ברישא. hai amar lei b'reisha. Now the גמרא gemara interjects. Well,
which of these two events happened first? It sounds clear, but the
גמרא gemara is going to reverse it. אילימא הך קמייתא, ilima hach
kamaisa, the one about plowing, אמר לו ברישא, amar lei b'reisha, הכא
נמי לימא אגיסטנא נבטוחא. hacha nami leima agis t'na nib'tocha. Once they
told him a guy could say that he's an imperial worker, so
he should have realized, and they could have told him that for
the second one, or he should have realized that they would have
told, they had that תירוץ teretz for the second guy. אלא האי
אמר לו ברישא. ela hai amar lei b'reisha. Okay, fine. The first
thing happened was the vineyard and then they were able to give
some excuse that he was using the wood for something else. והדר
אמר לו האי. v'hadar amar lei hai. And then he saw the
guy plowing, you have no excuse what you're plowing, and then they
had to give him the answer, well, he'll say he's an imperial
worker. Okay. Now, מאי שנא כהן? mai shna kohen? Now why did
ריש לקיש reish lakish particularly mention כהנים? kohanim? Oh, he's a כהן.
kohen. You could have just said because it made it more of
a violation. כהן kohen is supposed to be really פרום frum and
he's violating. But the גמרא gemara actually says no, משום דחשידי אשביעית.
mishum d'chashidei a'shvi'is. כהנים דווקא kohanim davka were חשוד chashud on שמיטה.
shmita רש"י rashi says that they sort of rationalized. They said, heck,
we're allowed to use תרומה. terumah. So if we're allowed to use
תרומה, terumah, like these things that are holy, maybe they're given for
us to use, and maybe therefore we can benefit from the שמיטה
shmita. produce even after the time is up to use them, maybe
we can plant the land on שמיטה. shmita They rationalized. How do
you know this? דתניא: d'tanya: סאה תרומה שנפלה למאה סאה של שביעית.
seah terumah she'nafla l'meah seah shel shvi'is. If a סאה seah of
תרומה terumah falls into a hundred of שמיטה shmita produce, תעלה. ta'aleh.
Then it's בטל. battel. And okay. פחות מכאן, pachot mikan, if it's
less than a hundred, ירקבו, yerakeivu, you have to let it rot
because you have to treat it as תרומה. terumah. ובעינן עלה, u'ba'inan
ala, מאי ירקבו? mai yerakeivu? Why do you have to let it
rot? אם תמצי לומר לכהן בדמי תרומה, im timtzei lomar l'kohen b'dmei
terumah, sell it to a כהן kohen at the prices of תרומה,
terumah, because he has to treat it all as תרומה terumah because
the תרומה terumah is not בטל. battel. So since he has to
treat it all as תרומה, terumah, it's not worth as much as
חולין. chullin. He has to be טהור, tahor, he has to be
careful with it, but at least sell it to him with those
prices.
חוץ מדמי אותה סאה, chutz m'dmei osah seah, and to sell him
a hundred units, not a hundred and one. So you're not
benefiting from the, you're not selling him תרומה. terumah. You're selling him
the hundred units. You're not selling him for the cost of a
hundred and one. You're doing it at the תרומה terumah price because
that's a fair price for him. He has to eat it as
תרומה. terumah. Why not do that? So basically why do you have
to let it all rot? So the גמרא gemara says, ואמר רבי
חייא משמיה דעולא, v'amar rabbi chiyya mishmei d'ulla, זאת אומרת, zos omeret,
this teaches you נחשדו כהנים אשביעית. nechsh'du kohanim a'shvi'is. You don't want
to sell him שמיטה shmita produce because if you sell him שמיטה
shmita produce, he'll eat it after the time he's no longer allowed
to eat it. Okay, so from here we infer since it didn't
give the option of selling this to a כהן, kohen, that you
can't trust a כהן kohen with שמיטה shmita, produce. Now it's one
thing to say that he'll eat it after the time he's supposed
to eat it. It's another thing to say that a כהן kohen
would actually go and work the land on שמיטה, shmita that's a
much clearer direct violation. But it sounds like in general they were
חשוד chashud and רש"י rashi says they rationalized, heck if we can
eat תרומה terumah and it's holy, we can work the land for
our own food. The תורה torah gives us an allowance to do
this work with this holy stuff and benefit from this holy stuff,
so let's work the land, let's eat the שמיטה shmita. produce. So
כהנים kohanim specifically were suspected. Now תוספות tosafot has a question: how
could we sell it to a כהן? kohen? You're not supposed to
do business with שמיטה. shmita So תוספות tosafot says there's a difference
doing business where you're doing it as a regular thing, buying and
selling and making a profit, or like a one-time sale. Like if
I went ahead and I collected some fruit for שמיטה shmita for
myself and I ate most of it and then there's a little
leftover, then I can sell it to Michael. That's not doing business.
That's like a chance occurrence. It's not like a regular type of
a thing. But that's interesting in terms of doing business with שמיטה
shmita, produce. Okay.
Meaning that here you're just selling just.
Yeah, just happened. It was a chance occurrence. It's not like you're
intending to do this and you're trying to make a profit from
it etc.
But you can't gather the other one where produce is only sold
once.
Right. If you're doing it to make a profit or whatever, right,
at least for that purpose, right, correct. Okay now, okay now the
גמרא gemara is not, now we're not done with this story with
ריש לקיש, reish lakish,
and so, כי מטו להתם, ki matu l'hasam, they finally got to
where they were going to do their עיבור שנה. ibur shana. כי
מטו להתם, ki matu l'hasam, סליקו לאיגרא. sliku l'igra. They went up
to the attic.
אמרו טורדא הוא דין. amru turda hu dein. So they, who was
it that ריש לקיש reish lakish was going along with? רבי חייא
בר זרנוקי ורבי שמעון בן יהוצדק. Rabbi Chiyya bar Zarnuki v'Rabbi Shimon
ben Yehotzadak. So they said, this guy's a pain in the neck,
talking about ריש לקיש. reish lakish. He's giving us all these hard
times. It's sort of like he's coming out of the ישיבה, yeshiva,
he doesn't appreciate the reality that people have to work the land
on
שמיטה, Shmita so he's דראינג אס א קאפ. draiying us a kop.
So let's get rid of him. So כי מטו להתם, ki matu
l'hasam, when they got to where they were going to do
the עיבור שנה, ibur shana, סליקו לאיגרא. sliku l'igra. They went up
to the
attic. So they said let's let's keep him out of here. He's
zoomin' anyway. Well true. אתא לקמיה דרבי יוחנן ata lekamei deReb Yochanan
so ריש לקיש Resh Lakish came for רבי יוחנן. Reb Yochanan. אמר
להו amar lehu he said to them: בני אדם החשודים על השביעית
כשרים לעבר השנה? bnei adam hachashudim al hashvi'is ksherim le'aber hashanah? He
says people that are חשודים chashudim on שמיטה Shmita? they're not standing
up are they כשרים to do עיבור שנה ibbur shanah which echoes
back our משנה Mishna because who's פסול in our משנה Mishna the
people that do business on שמיטה? Shmita So these people are passively
condoning this type of stuff on שמיטה Shmita. and you're going to
let them they're כשר to do עיבור שנה? ibbur shanah? הדר אמר
hadar amar then ריש לקיש Resh Lakish said you know what
maybe I can rational explain how it's okay for them to do
עיבור שנה. ibbur shanah. מני דהוה אשלשה רועי בקר. mani dehavah ashlosha
ro'ei bakar. It was like these cowherds you remember the story it
was these cowherds were talking about the about the weather and the
agriculture and the rabbis used that to determine whether to do an
עיבור שנה. ibbur shana. Fine they'll be like cowherds. And by the
way it also echoes the fact that the משנה says that who's
פסול is not only סוחרי שביעית but רועי צאן. ro'ei tzon. And
there was a discussion of רועי בקר ro'ei bakar so they're like
it's echoing all those cases of who's פסול. But those people are
כשר to do עיבור שנה. ibbur shana. רבנן אחושבנייהו סמכו rabbanan achushvanyehu
samchu and the rabbis relied on their ruling on their on the
calculations of these cowherds. So here too they can
be part of the שמיטה. Shmita Be cowherds. הדר אמר hadar amar
you know what לא דמי. lo dami. Actually it's not a good
comparison. התם hasam הדר אימנו רבנן ועיברוה לההיא שתא. hadar imnu rabbanan
ve'ibruha lehahi shata. There the cowherds said something then the rabbis got
together and just based on the discussion of the cowherds did their
own חשבון cheshbon but it was the rabbis who were making the
עיבור שנה. ibbur shana. הכא hacha here
it's the same rabbis who tolerated the violation of שמיטה Shmita they
themselves are doing the עיבור שנה. ibbur shana. So it's not just
other rabbis are relying on them. קשר רשעים הוא. kesher resha'im hu.
It's a band of wicked people. וקשר רשעים אינו מן המנין. ve-kesher
resha'im eino min haminyan. They can't be part of the convocation to
make the עיבור שנה. ibbur shana. They're not just people that are
giving evidence talking about the agriculture. So basically okay. So אמר
רבי יוחנן amar Reb Yochanan so highly critical of the way they
tolerate this שמיטה Shmita. violation. אמר רבי יוחנן amar Reb Yochanan רבי
יוחנן Reb Yochanan said דעקא da'aka oh that hurts. To call these
people רשעים. resha'im. Okay that's going a little too far ריש לקיש.
Resh Lakish. That was all he said. Okay כי אתו לקמי דרבי
יוחנן ki atu lekamei deReb Yochanan now when these rabbis came to
רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan well yeah like like okay. כי אתו לקמי
דרבי יוחנן ki atu lekamei deReb Yochanan אמרו ליה: amru lei: קרי
לן רועי בקר ולא אמר ליה מר ולא מידי? kari lan ro'ei
bakar velo amar lei mar velo midi?
Your student your colleague ריש לקיש Resh Lakish called us cowherds and
you didn't stand up. You only stood up for us when he
called us רשעים. resha'im. You didn't say anything when he was calling
us cowherds. אמר להו amar lehu he said to them: ואי קרא
לכם רועי צאן מה אמינא ליה? ve'ikra lachem ro'ei tzon mah amina
lei? And even if he had called you even if he called
you like shepherds or whatever they're called
shepherds. There you go shepherds. If he called you shepherds what should
I have said? Because shepherds are worse than cowherds as we learned
yesterday. What should I say? He's right. You were tolerating a violation
of שמיטה. Shmita Okay you're not
רשעים resha'im but still you should be doing something more to stand
up for it. So it's very interesting where the ירושלמי Yerushalmi which
was living with this reality cast never had one slight hint of
any of any problem with the fact that people were violating and
basically indicated that it was פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. In the בבלי
Bavli there's no hint that it's
פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh which is why תוספות tosafot says maybe they
think that שמיטה is דרבנן. de-rabbanan. And clear the whole discussion ends
with a very critical at least being critical if not of the
people that themselves are doing it but at least of the rabbis
for not caring more and trying to do more to counteract that.
So it's very interesting if you're not like living the circumstances it's
easier to be a little bit more critical about what's going on.
Yes.
רבה Rava רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish were
both אמוראים Amora'im in the land of Israel.
Right but this is the בבלי's Bavli version of what they said.
Okay so okay. By the way it's very interesting because I think
one of these rabbis who was part of this עיבור שנה ibbur
shana which was רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק Reb Shimon ben Yehotzadak if
I remember correctly he was the one who was also quoted in
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi in the פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh discussion. Anyway now
that we mentioned קשר רשעים kesher resha'im we're going to have a
little אגדתא aggadatic digression. Okay מאי קשר רשעים mai kesher resha'im what
is this what is this קשר רשעים? kesher resha'im? שבנא shevna הוה
דריש בתליסר רבוותא. havah darish bilsarei rivvatha. Where do we get this
concept that there's an idea of קשר רשעים kesher resha'im and that
they're not מן המנין? min haminyan? So שבנא shevna who was חזקיהו's
Chizkiyahu sort of like second-in-command there so he this is now אגדתא
aggadatic okay but it's based on a story in the in the
תנ"ך. Tanakh. He when he would give teach תורה Torah classes because
everybody was a rabbi in the old days so he הוה דריש
בתליסר רבוותא havah darish bilsarei rivvatha he would have thirteen myriads 130,000.
people attended his שיעור. shiur.
חזקיה הוה דרש בחדסר רבוותא.
Hizkiya hava darash
be-hadasar rivvosa. חזקיה Hizkiya only had 11 myriads listening to his שיעורים.
shiurim. So שבנא Shevna thought he was all, you know, hot stuff.
So כי אתא סנחריב, ki ata Sanheriv, now when סנחריב Sanheriv came
וצר על ירושלים ve-tzar al Yerushalayim and basically besieged Jerusalem, כתב שבנא
פתקא, ktav Shevna pitka, Shevna wrote a little note to him,
ושדא בגירא, ve-shada be-gira, he shot it with an arrow out to
סנחריב. Sanheriv. And here's what the note said: שבנא וסיעתיה, Shevna ve-siatei,
Shevna and all of his group, his, you know, 13
myriads, השלימו hishlimu already to make peace with you and basically we'll
open up the gates let you come in and take over ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. חזקיה וסיעתיה לא השלימו, Hizkiya ve-siatei lo hishlimu, but חזקיה Hizkiya
and his group don't want to make peace. שנאמר, shene'emar, now how
do we know he did this? כי הנה הרשעים
ידרכון קשת, ki hinei ha-rshaim yidrechun keshet, the wicked people will like,
you know, pull the bow, stretch the bow, כוננו חצם על יתר,
konenun hitzam al yeter, they will sort of they will they will
like, you know, shoot their arrows, you know, guide their arrows to
יתר, yeter, and יתר yeter means more because he had more people.
So he thought that he was going to be, he was better
and he was going to, you know, be able to determine it.
הוה קא מסתפי חזקיה, hava ka mistafi Hizkiya, חזקיה Hizkiya was afraid.
אמר דילמא חס ושלום נטייה דעתיה דקודשא בריך הוא בתר רובא, amar
dilma chas ve-shalom natya daatei de-kudsha brich hu batar ruba, right? מה
דאמר, ma de-amar, what was it? אחרי רבים
להטות. acharei rabim le-hatot. מה דאמר? ma de-amar? מה דאמר? ma de-amar?
לא תטה. lo tateh. No, it's
not לא תטה, lo tateh, I'm getting confused, but there's a word
נוטה noteh there anyway. So anyway, okay, anyway maybe God, נתן עריב
ליטות אחרי רבים להטות,
natan
areiv
litot acharei rabim le-hatot, right? So maybe God is being נוטה noteh
by the רבים rabim
because he has more
people, but it's like לא תעלה וליטות אחרי רבים. lo taaleh ve-litot
acharei rabim. נטייה דעתיה דקודשא בריך הוא בתר רובא. natya daatei de-kudsha
brich hu batar ruba. כיוון דרובא מימסרי keivan de-ruba mimsarei and if
the majority is ready to hand, to give over, to, you know,
surrender, אינהו נמי מימסרי, inhu nami mimsarei, we should also surrender. בא
נביא ואמר לו, ba navi ve-amar lo, the נביא navi came and
said to him, לא תאמרון קשר לכל אשר יאמר העם הזה קשר,
lo tomrun kesher le-chol asher yomar ha-am ha-zeh kesher, don't say like
a band, all these people say a band. כלומר, klomar, קשר רשעים
הוא, kesher reshaim hu, ah, they might be the majority, but they're
wicked people, וקשר רשעים אינו מן המנין ve-kesher reshaim eino min ha-minyan
and the band of wicked people don't count towards the majority. Don't
worry, you got the majority on your side. Okay. אזל למיחצב ליה
קברא, azal le-michzav lei kivra, now שבנא Shevna again thought he was
such hot stuff. He went to dig for himself a grave or
like a sepulchre בקברי בית דוד be-kivrei beis Dovid amongst those of
the kings of David. He thought that he was better than חזקיה.
Hizkiya. בא נביא ואמר לו, ba navi ve-amar lo, the נביא navi
came and said to him, מה לך פה ומי לך פה כי
חצבת לך פה קבר, ma lecha po u-mi lecha po ki chatzavta
lecha po kaver, what makes you think you deserve to dig a
grave here? הנה ה' מטלטלך טלטלה גבר, hinei Hashem metaltelecha taltela gaver,
God will make you sort of wander, go in exile like that
of the exile of a man. אמר רב, said Rav, טלטולא דגברא
קשיא מדאיתתא. taltula de-gavra kashya mi-de-itata. Since he said גבר gaver of
a man, so you see when a man goes into exile, it's
harder than him than when a woman goes into exile. I don't
know, all I know is that whenever we go on vacation, my
wife does not like us sleeping in houses that are not her
own. But anyway,
okay.
ואתך עטה, ve-atecha ata, so what does this mean? Cover you with
a cover, what's that mean? אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, amar Rabbi
Yossi barabi Chanina, מלמד שפרחה בו צרעת, melamed she-parcha bo tzaraas, so
שבנא Shevna had צרעת tzaraas cover him. כתיב הכא ואתך עטה ksiv
hacha ve-atecha ata וכתיב התם ועל שפם יעטה. u-ksiv hasam ve-al safam
yaateh. Okay, the end of the פסוק pasuk now is
צנוף יצנפך צניפה כדור אל ארץ רחבת ידים. tzanof yitznefecha tznifa ka-dur
el eretz rachavat yadayim. So it's a little unclear what that means.
תוספות Tosafos anyway says it means he'll roll you like a ball
in a wide land. תנא, tana, הוא ביקש קלון בית אדוניו לכן
כבודו
לקלון נהפך כבודו לקלון.
hu bikesh kalon beis adonav lachen kvodo le-kalon
nehpach
kvodo le-kalon. He wanted to embarrass his master's house, חזקיה, Hizkiya, therefore
his honor turned into embarrassment. Okay. כי הוי נפיק, ki hava nafik,
now back to the story. He was going out. He still wanted
to take his 130,000 people with him to make peace with סנחריב.
Sanheriv. כי הוי נפיק אתא גבריאל ואחדיה לדשא באפי משירייתא. ki hava
nafik ata Gavriel ve-achadei le-dasha be-appei mashiryasa. So Gabriel closed the door
and cut him off from his, from all of his attendants. So
he went down, you know, and he thought he had 130,000 people
behind him but Gabriel had, you know, closed the door and they
weren't able to get out of the city. אמרו ליה, amru lei,
so they said to him, סנחריב's Sanheriv troops, משירייתך היכא, mashiryasach heicha,
where are all of your attendants? Where's that whole band of people
you said you had? אמר הדרי בי, amar hadrei bi, they must
have abandoned me. אמרו ליה, amru lei, they said to him, אם
כן אחוכי קמחייכת בן, im ken achochei kamchaichet ban, so you're, you're
making a mockery of us. שנקבוהו בעקביו, shenikvohu be-ikvav, they pierced his,
his, his heels and ותלאוהו בזנבי סוסיהם ve-taluohu be-zanvei suseihem and they
suspended him from the, from the, the tails of their, of their
horses. והיו מגררים אותו על הקוצים ועל הברקנים ve-hayu megarerim oso al
ha-kotzim ve-al ha-barkanim and they'd, and they'd drag him, the horses, you
know, would drag him. all over the thorns and the thistles. אמר
רבי אליעזר, Amar Rabbi Eliezer, so he got his comeuppance, אמר and
that's probably also what it says that you know he'll drag you
along and like the exile of a person. What?
And the heels, that goes with exile.
Oh, wait, wait, wait, back
up, it's the sensitive whatever. Oh, right, right, right.
The whole, the
whole
body, right, it's the heels, right. אמר רבי אליעזר שבנא בעל הנאה
היה, Amar Rabbi Eliezer Shevna ba'al hana'ah hayah, he was a, you
know, he was somebody who was, lusted after pleasure.
Others call it a hedonist.
Hedonist, okay. Is the
what do you call? I looked Sansino called it a sybarite. Have
you ever heard the word a sybarite? You could look that up
in your OED. Okay. כתיב הכא ksiv hacha here it says לך
בא אל הסוכן, lech bo el ha-sochen, go to the, which is
ואז va-az וכתיב התם u-chsiv hatam ותהי לו סוכנת va-tehi lo sochenes
by David and Avishag.
So it refers to sexual pleasure. Okay. Now, one more pasuk about
this: כי השתות יהרסון צדיק מה פעל. Ki ha-shatos yeharesun tzaddik mah
pa'al.
If the foundation is destroyed, what will the righteous one have done?
So what does that mean?
What? The? Okay. רב יהודה ורב עינא,
Rav
Yehuda
ve-Rav Ina, חד אמר
chad amar אלו חזקיה וסיעתו נהרסו, eilu Chizkiyah ve-si'ato nehersu, had Hezekiah
and his,
you know, group, his, you know, his followers, been destroyed? Had Shevna
succeeded? צדיק מה פעל, tzaddik mah pa'al, what could God, here refers
to God, what could God have done? How would God have been
able to pay back Hezekiah for his righteousness? וחד אמר ve-chad amar
אלו בית המקדש נהרס. eilu Beis Ha-Mikdash neheras. No, the is the
foundation. Had Sennacherib won, had Shevna succeeded, and Sennacherib would have entered
and destroyed the Beis Ha-Mikdash, צדיק מה פעל, tzaddik mah pa'al, where
would have been God's promises, you know, and God's and God's wonders?
ועולא אמר ve-Ulla amar אלו מחשבותיו של אותו רשע אינם נהרסות. eilu
machshavosav shel oso rasha einam neharasos. No, it it means the opposite,
that the, the the plot had to be destroyed, 'cause had the
plot not been destroyed, צדיק מה פעל, tzaddik mah pa'al, where would
have been God's doing? Okay, so בשלמא למאן דאמר bishelama le-man de-amar
אלו מחשבותיו של אותו רשע, eilu machshavosav shel oso rasha, היינו דכתיב
hainu de-chsiv כי השתות יהרסון. ki ha-shatos yeharesun. The word here means
it means foundation, but it's translated as Rashi says לא שת לבו,
lo shas libo, like to place your heart to something, your plans,
you you know, your schemes. So that means the schemes were destroyed.
ולמאן דאמר בית המקדש נמי, u-le-man de-amar Beis Ha-Mikdash nami, how does
the word refer to the Beis Ha-Mikdash? דתנן di-tnan אבן הייתה שם
מימות נביאים ראשונים ושתייה הייתה נקראת. even haysah sham mi-yemos nevi'im rishonim
u-shsiyah haysah nikre'is. Right, the, the foundation stone. Okay, so that would
be a way it refers to had the Beis Ha-Mikdash been destroyed,
right, God's plan would have been, you know, destroyed would have been
frustrated. אלא למאן דאמר חזקיה וסיעתו, ela le-man de-amar Chizkiyah ve-si'ato, but
if it refers to Hezekiah, היכא אשכחן צדיקי דאיקרו שתות? heicha ashkechan
tzaddiki de-ikru shatos? Where do we find that are called like the
foundation?
דכתיב de-chsiv כי לה' מצוקי ארץ, ki l'Hashem metzukei eretz, God has
the pillars of the land, וישת עליהם תבל, va-yashes aleihem tevel, and
he places the earth upon them. So basically what it's suggesting is
is that, you know, that they represent Torah. And Torah is the
foundation of the world. So those that follow the Torah and that
are righteous or Torah scholars, they are, you know, therefore that refers
to them as the. איבעית אימא מהכא Iba'is eima mehacha הפליא עצה,
hifli eitzah, the wisdom is great, הגדיל תושיה, higdil tushiyah, the understanding
also is great. And here referring to Torah. So Torah is the
foundation. I don't know exactly the word, whatever. But anyway, and therefore
that refers to Hezekiah, therefore his his plan could not have been
destroyed, 'cause then what would have happened? אמר רב חנן Amar Rav
Chanan למה נקרא שמה תושיה? lamah nikra shemah tushiyah? Why is the
Torah called? מפני שהיא מתשת כוחו של אדם, mipnei she-hi masheshes kocho
shel adam, because you learn a lot of Torah and it it
it weakens
you. So, דבר אחר davar acher תושיה שניתנה בחשאי, tushiyah she-nisnah be-chashai,
it was given in in in
like in in secret or in, you know, private, in quiet, not
not public. מפני השטן, mipnei ha-satan, because of the. So what does
that mean? I mean, the first giving of the were quite public.
But it probably refers to the second giving of the. דבר אחר
davar acher or maybe it means not when it was given initially.
What?
קול דממה דקה,
kol
demamah dakkah, right. The second, but I think the second is particularly
what's
given. דבר אחר davar acher תושיה דברים של תוהו שהעולם משתת עליהם.
tushiyah devarim shel tohu she-ha-olam mishtates aleihem. He has a very beautiful
idea. He says Torah is just words. Words have no physical substance.
It's just air. So this is so inconsequential, the words of Torah,
if you think physically, right, it's nothing. Where's where are the words?
Where are they? And nevertheless, the world is supported on them. So
these words of of this thing that has no physical form, ultimately,
you know, sustains the world. The world is supported on them. אמר
עולא. Amar Ulla. What?
I mean, an expression of Hashem, no physical form, he created the
whole world.
Right, exactly. Okay. אמר עולא. Amar Ulla. Now, one last interesting idea
about this: מחשבה מועלת
אפילו לדברי
תורה. Machshavah mo'eles afilu le-divrei Torah. Words, thoughts. Help, but help doesn't
mean help here, it means hurt. You should know, תורה Torah is
so wonderful, but if you are always anxious and always thinking, you
know, worried about things, they will impact even your ability to learn
תורה. Torah. Okay, so those troublesome thoughts, שנאמר, shene'emar, מפר מחשבות ערומים
ולא תעשינה ידיהם תושיה. mefir machshavos arumim velo sa'asena yedeihem tushiya.
God, you know, sort of undoes the plans and the thoughts of
the wise ones or whatever, and the, and their hands cannot do
תושיה, tushiya, they can't learn תורה. Torah. So, you know, so if
you're if you're
too preoccupied with your thoughts, it'll get in the way of your
learning תורה. Torah. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, but he must
say עוסקים לשמה אינם מועלת. asukim lishmah einam moeles. If you're learning
תורה Torah לשמה, lishmah, then your thoughts will not distract you. שנאמר,
shene'emar, רבות מחשבות בלב איש ועצת השם
היא תקום. rabos machshavos be-lev ish va'atzas Hashem hi sakum. עצה שיש
בה דבר השם, etza sheyeish bah devar Hashem, if it's actually it's
all about God, then היא תקום לעולם, hi sakum le'olam, then that
will be established. He won't let your more worldly or other type
of anxious thoughts get in the way. You'll be able to focus
on your תורה Torah and everything else will sort of fall aside.
Okay, so we will end here and we will